McLennan County Democratic Party records, Inclusive: 1922-1992, undated; Bulk: 1970-1979
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
McLennan County Democratic Party records
Inclusive: 1922-1992, undated; Bulk: 1970-1979
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
16
McLennan County Democratic Party; Evans, Gene, 1941-2005, 1941 - 2005
5 document boxes.
The McLennan County Democratic Party records contain meeting minutes, financial records, ballots, and other election materials from the mid-twentieth century. The collection was donated by Gene Evans, a former chair of the organization.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Waco was the site of Texas's first Democratic Convention in 1857. Since 1873, Waco Democrats have served in influential positions throughout state and national politics. The party maintained dominance in the local area for much of the twentieth century.
After Dr. Walter William resigned as McLennan County Democratic Chairman in 1979, the Executive Committee appointed Gene Evans to serve the remainder of William's term until 1980. Evans ultimately served as Chair until the fall of 1988 when his term expired. After his tenure, Evans donated various party records to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library.
Four of the most significant changes that impacted the McLennan County Democratic Party while Evans was chair were the discontinuation of voting by paper ballot, the election of the first Republican governor of Texas since Reconstruction, redistricting, and presidential primaries. It is noteworthy that McLennan County was one of the last Texas counties to discontinue the use of a paper ballot.
Scope and Content
The McLennan County Democratic Party records cover a broad portion of the twentieth century, from 1922 to 1992. The majority of the materials span the chairmanships of Walter William and Gene Evans, focusing particularly on the 1970's.
Series I. Democratic Executive Committee and Series II. Election Materials are the largest series in the collection. The records address a variety of local issues, including the discontinuation of paper ballots, redistricting, and presidential primaries. There is a wide range of materials in the collection including correspondence, financial reports, ballot results, newspaper clippings, and minutes.
Arrangement
The collection was originally housed in acidic boxes. Inventories were created by staff members in 1993 and 1998, but no finding aid existed prior to this current round of processing.
The original order of the collection has largely been maintained. The records are now arranged into four series based on material type: I. Democratic Executive Committee, II. Election Materials, III. Financial Records, and IV. Subject Files.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 16. Acquired 1993-01-27
Related Resources
Related references
“A Brief History of the McLennan County Democratic Party.” McLennan County Democratic Party: 200th Anniversary, July 1992.
“H. Gene Evans.” "Waco Tribune-Herald." Accessed September 10, 2020.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Democratic Party (Tex.); Democratic Party (U.S.)
Places
McLennan County (Tex.) -- History.; McLennan County (Tex.) -- Politics and government.
Subjects
Elections -- Texas.; Political campaigns -- Texas -- McLennan County.; Primaries -- Texas.; Voting -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Election returns.; Financial records.; Minutes (Records); Registers (Lists).; Resolutions (Law)
- Democratic Executive Committee, 1922-1984; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I contains correspondence, meeting minutes, propositions, resolutions, charts, lists, and election results pertaining to the Executive Committee of the McLennan County Democratic Party. Most folders deal directly with the Democratic primaries held in the 1970's, although the minutes for the committee stretch as far back as the early 1920's. The materials are in average condition.
  - 1976 Democratic National Convention, Delegate Selection Plan (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1970 Democratic Primary, Election Results (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1972 Democratic Primary, Candidates (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, List, Candidates, Judges (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, List, Clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Referendum Results (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, Correspondence, Clippings, and Map (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Campaign Headquarters and Organizational Chart, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Candidate and Committee Meetings, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee Material, General, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Application for Sheriff, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Constitutional Revision Commission, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, List, Candidates, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - List, Committee Members, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - List, Committee Members, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - List, Committee, Candidates, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Memorandum, Meeting Agenda, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum, Meeting Agenda, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Meeting Minutes and Resolutions, 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1948-1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Memorandum, Opinion, Order, Redistricting, Residency, Filing, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Plans, Statistics, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Presiding Judge Folder, Return of a Primary Election, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Primaries, Candidates, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Resolutions, General, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Resolutions, Propositions, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rules of the Democratic Party of Texas, 1974 National Conference on Democratic Party Organization and Policy, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Secretary of State, Directives, Voting, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Texas Election Code, Financing of Primaries, Correspondence, Bills, Resolutions, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Election Materials, 1949-1980, undated; 2
  Series II. Election Materials contains ballot counts, applications for a place on the ballot, precinct information, lists of candidates, and lists of registered voters. Most of the materials relate to Democratic primaries from the 1970's, though some folders do address statewide politics. The series is in average condition.
  - 1968 Democratic Primary, Ballot Count (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1970 Democratic Primary, Application for a Place on the Ballot, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1970 Democratic Primary, Election Judges (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1972 Democratic Primary, Application for a Place on the Ballot, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1972 Democratic Primary, Election Results (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1972 Democratic Primary, Return of a Primary Election (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Application for a Place on the Ballot, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, List, Candidates (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Precinct Ballot Information, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1976 Democratic Primary, List, Candidates (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, Application for a Place on the Ballot (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, Application for a Place on the Ballot (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, Ballot (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, List, Candidates, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, Election Judges (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ballot Tallies, Democratic Primary, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Blank Ballot Applications, Correspondence, 1952-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Booklets, “Election Laws Passed by the 60th Legislature”, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Absentee Voting, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - List, Democratic County Chairmen of Texas, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - List of Boxes, “Guide to Voting Precincts”, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - List of Voting Boxes, 1948-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Location of Voting Boxes, 1972-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Maps, Texas Congressional District, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Map of Waco, Councilmen’s Wards, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Precinct Lines and Redistricting, 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Registered Voter by Election Precinct (1 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Registered Voter by Election Precinct (2 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Registered Voter by Election Precinct (3 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Tally of Registered Voters by Precinct, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Voter Registration, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Financial Records, 1933-1986, undated; 3
  Series III. Financial Records contains expense accounts, financial reports, receipts, ledgers, and recommendations. Most of the materials relate directly to Democratic primaries held during the 1970's. The series also has a ledger dating back to the mid-1930's. The materials that comprise this series are in average condition.
  - 1970 Democratic Primary, Expense Account (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1972 Democratic Primary, Account for Holding Election (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1972 Democratic Primary, Expense Report (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Account for Holding Election (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Budget (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Expense Account (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Expense Estimates, Indexes (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1974 Democratic Primary, Financial Statement (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1976 Democratic Primary, Financial Statement (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1978 Democratic Primary, Expense Reports (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cash, Receipts, Disbursements, 1933-1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Costs of Implementation of the Federal Voting Rights Act, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Democratic Primary, Budget, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Exemptions, Reports, Payments, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Expense Report, Democratic Primaries, 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Expense Report, Democratic Primaries, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Financial Report, Supporting Candidates for Nomination or for Election as a United States Senator, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Financial Reports, General, 1943-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - “Index to Primary Financing Rules”, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Ledger, 1934-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ledger, 1974-1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Primary Election, Expense Report, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Recommendations, Reports, 1966-1974 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Subject Files, 1972-1992; 4
  Series IV. Subject Files contains several files arranged by subject. The material covers a wide range of topics including Billy Goldberg, Gene Evans, Lyndon B. Johnson, party leadership, and the two hundredth anniversary of the McClennan County Democratic Party. Overall, this series is in average condition.
  - 200th Anniversary, Program, Independence Day Rally, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Billy Goldberg, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Gene Evans, 1972-1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson, Booklet, “LBJ: Images of a Vibrant Life”, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Party Leadership, 1979-1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Resolutions, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - San Marcos Baptist Academy, Booklet, “Building a New Home”, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)